Guide to the Janelle Lynch Photographs 2001-2006 PR 344
New-York Historical Society
Janelle Lynch photographs
2001-2006
New-York Historical Society
Lynch, Janelle
PR 344
2 Linear feet in one flat box
The collection includes eleven photographs from Janelle Lynch's series "River, 2001-2006." The photographs generally include views of the lower Hudson River, with views typically facing west from Manhattan toward New Jersey, foregrounded by decaying piers, pilings, twisted ironwork, the Holland Tunnel air shafts, or other such features of the shoreline's built environment.
Scope and Contents Note
The collection includes eleven photographs from Janelle Lynch's series "River, 2001-2006." The photographs are untitled, but numbered 1 through 10, with two prints of #2. All photographs are 20 x 24 inches. Most are in color, with two in black and white. The container list records the individual photographs and indicates the edition number (not all photographs are marked with an edition number).
The photographs generally include views of the lower Hudson River, with views typically facing west from Manhattan toward New Jersey (Jersey City, Hoboken, Weehawken area). Many views have decaying piers, pilings, twisted ironwork or other such features of the shoreline's built environment in the foreground. The Holland Tunnel air shafts appear prominently in some. #5 highlights the abandoned New York Central Railroad's 69th Street Transfer Bridge.
Arrangement Note
The collection was acquired in three accessions over time. The collection is held in three folders, with each folder holding one of these accessions.
Biographical/Historical Note
Janelle Lynch (b. 1969) is an American large-format landscape photographer. Lynch's photographs form part of public and private collections worldwide, including, among others, New York's Metropolitan Museum of Art. She has exhibited internationally and her work has been written about and published in international periodicals and journals. She is a faculty member at the International Center of Photography and an occasional contributor to Afterimage, The Photo Review, and photo-eye. In 1999, Lynch received an MFA in Photography from the School of Visual Arts, where she studied with Stephen Shore and Joel Sternfeld. In 2003, she completed the Master Class in Photography, a one-on-one tutorial, with Shore at Bard College. Since 2015 she has been studying drawing and painting at The New York Studio School with Graham Nickson.
(The above note was abstracted from Lynch's biographical note on her website at: https://www.janellelynch.net.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photographs.; Piers -- New York (State) -- New York.; New York Harbor (N.Y. and N.J.); Jersey City (N.J.).; Hudson River (N.Y. and N.J.); Lynch, Janelle
- Untitled 2 [Hudson River], color, 2001 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  Immediate Source of Acquisition Note
  Gift of Janelle Lynch, 2014.
  Scope and Contents Note
  This photograph was originally held in the Photographer's File (PR 50). It was moved to this collection (PR 344) in October 2017 when additional Lynch photographs were acquired.
- Untitled 5 [69th Street Transfer Bridge], ed. 4/6, b&w, 2001-2006 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  Purchase, 2016.
- Untitled 1, ed. 3/6, color, 2001-2006 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  All photographs in folder 3 were purchased in 2017.
- Untitled 2, ed. 4/6, color, 2001-2006 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
- Untitled 3, ed. 5/6, color, 2001-2006 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
- Untitled 4, ed. 6/6, color, 2001-2006 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
- Untitled 6, color, 2001-2006 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
- Untitled 7, b&w, 2001-2006 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
- Untitled 8, ed. 5/6, color, 2001-2006 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
- Untitled 9, color, 2001-2006 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
- Untitled 10, ed. 4/6, color, 2001-2006 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)